A nobody
무명소졸이라
Not worth mentioning
말해 줄 것도 없다
I'll remember your face
네 놈 얼굴을 똑똑히 기억해 주마!
Retreat
철수한다!
Brothers
형제들이여!
Pursue with all our might
전력으로 추격하여 다 쓸어버리자!
Wait
잠깐만
Chen Ying
진응
You still want to stop us?
왜 또 막아요?
I've already given you all my military merit
이미 내 전공을 전부 양보했잖아요
You dare go back on your word
감히 한 입으로 두말해요
General Zu
조 장군
I only promised to hold Yiyang
난 익양성을 지킨다고만 했네
Pursuing the Wuzhao is too risky
오노를 추격하는 건 위험 부담이 너무 크오
All soldiers
장병들이여
The Wuzhao trampled the central plains
오노는 중원을 침략하고
Oppressed our people
우리 동포를 괴롭혔다
If we let the Wuzhao return north
이대로 쉽게 보내주면
Next time those who suffer
다음에 수난 당하는 건
May be your families
너희들의 가족이거나
And friends
친구가 될 것이다
Sons of Xuan
선국의 사내들이
How can we endure such humiliation?
어째서 이런 치욕을 당해야 하는가?
Northern volunteers
북방의 의군들마저
Still dare to fight to the death
목숨을 걸고 적과 싸웠다
Those with courage
배짱이 있는 놈들은
Follow me and kill
나를 따라 돌격하라!
Without my order
내 명령 없이는 아무도 움직이지 마라!
Kill
돌격!
The sun sets
태양이 저물 무렵
Liu Dadao, at some point
유대도는 언제부턴가
Was pierced by a spear
이미 긴 창에 꿰뚫려
Kneeling backward in the sunset
하늘을 올려보며 무릎을 꿇고 쓰러졌습니다
On both sides of him
그의 양옆으로
Xuan's iron cavalry thundered past
선국의 철기병이 바람을 가르며 돌진했고
He gazed at the pink sky
붉게 물든 하늘을 바라보며
Finally released the blade in his hand
마침내 손에 쥔 대도를 놓았습니다
Facing death
죽음을 앞에 두고
Who isn't afraid?
누가 두려워하지 않겠는가
Who isn't a coward?
누가 겁쟁이가 아니겠는가
But there are always some beliefs
하지만 어떤 신념은
That can support
겁쟁이도
A coward's backbone
어깨를 펴게 하지요
Liu
유
Liu Nian
유염
I, Sikong Yao, swear
나 사공요가 맹세하네
I will protect her
내가 반드시 그녀를
Warm clothes and full bellies
옷과 끼니를 챙겨주고
Peace and happiness
평안하게 살게 해주겠네
General Liu
유 장군
You and the brothers
형제들과 함께
Rest assured
편히 잠드시게
The imperial physicians said
어의가 그랬어요
Not to get too emotional
너무 흥분하면 안 된다고요
Your head condition
이 병은 안정을 취해야 한대요
Those physicians
어의들이 뭘 안다고
The Daoist masters said
도사들이 말하기를
Three disasters, nine hardships, ten trials
3재 9난 10겁을 넘겨야
Must pass through to achieve immortality
장수할 수 있다고 했소
Born
태어났어요
How is it?
어떻게 됐어?
Congratulations, Your Majesty
감축드립니다
Congratulations, Empress
폐하, 황후마마
It's a son
귀한 손주를 얻으셨습니다
Good
좋아
I will richly reward the Xie family
사 씨에게 후한 상을 내려야겠어
Let's go
갑시다
I want to see my grandson
손주를 봐야지
Look at him
이것 좀 보시오
He's smiling, he's smiling
애가 웃고 있소
His eyes
눈은 아비를 닮았고
His nose
코는
Takes after me
짐을 닮았구려
This is the eldest grandson
이 아이 장손입니다
Your Majesty should give him a name
페하께서 이름을 지어주세요
Good
그렇지
Sheng
성(盛)
Call him
이 아이의 이름은
Sikong Sheng
사공성이다
Father is wise
부황, 영명하십시다
Sheng
성(盛)은
Is for the great victory in the north
북방 대첩의 승리를 의미하며
Is for the north-south canal
이제 곧 완성될
Soon to be opened for prosperity
남북 운하의 번영을 의미하며
Is from heaven
하늘이 우리 선나라 국운을
Blessing Great Xuan's flourishing fortune
번성케 한다는 의미도 됩니다
We
우리 좋은 며느리를 뒀어요
Sheng'er
성아